Theodore Roosevelt Collection
Theodore Roosevelt Collection
1882-1925
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.
1.0 linear ft.
Outgoing correspondence, photographs, articles, speeches by and about Roosevelt; miscellaneous memorial material.
2618833
Biographical History
Theodore Roosevelt (1858-1919), also known as "Teddy," was the twenty-sixth President of the United States and a leader of the Republican Party and of the Progressive Movement. His public service career included serving as Governor of New York, Assistant Secretary of the Navy, and vice president to William McKinley, whom he succeeded as President upon McKinley's assassination in 1901. His reformist policies, collectively referred to as the "Square Deal", have led historians to view him as one of the ablest presidents and an icon of the Progressive Era. In addition to his political achievements, he was a historian, naturalist, explorer, author, and soldier.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Theodore Roosevelt Collection consists of outgoing correspondence, photographs, articles and speeches by and about Roosevelt, including some produced for memorial services, and a small amount of miscellanea.
Correspondence, ranging from 1882-1918, is largely from Theodore Roosevelt, with a small amount of routine family correspondence included. Family represented: Edith Kermit Roosevelt (wife), Theodore Roosevelt, Jr. (son), Ethel Roosevelt (daughter), and Corinne Roosevelt Robinson (sister). One of the most interesting family letters is from Edith, Sept. 22 (no year), referring to Roosevelt's surprise at his sudden elevation to the office of President of the United States.
Of special interest are the bound transcripts of an extensive exchange between Roosevelt and Henry Cabot Lodge (1850-1924). Running from 1884-1918, the letters are titled, "Secret history of man and events through his entire public career amazingly revealed in intimate epistles," and are heavily political and personal. The letters were published in 1925 by Charles Scribner's Sons as "Selections from the correspondence of Theodore Roosevelt and Henry Cabot Lodge, 1884-1918."
The Photographs depict Roosevelt as Rough Rider and on the campaign trail. Family members are present in many of the news photographs.
Writings contains articles and speeches by and about Roosevelt, including numerous memorial tributes and speeches.
Miscellaneous material consists of campaigning itineraries and a photograph of Deadwood, South Dakota Sheriff Seth Bullock, a long-time friend of Roosevelt.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into outgoing and incoming. Outgoing is arranged in chronological order, apart from family correspondence which follows. Incoming from others is filed at the end of Correspondence. All other material is in no particular order.
Related Material
See also the
Paul Richards Theodore Roosevelt Collection
.
has made a concerted effort over the years to ensure that its manuscript and rare books holdings complement each other. As a result, many of our manuscript collections are supported by books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection. Please be sure to search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Bullock, Seth, 1849-1919.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1887-1944.; United States. -- Army. -- Volunteer Cavalry, 1st.; Articles.; Correspondence.; Itineraries.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Politicians -- United States.; Presidents -- United States.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Bullock photograph gift of Cliff Strait; portions purchased; portions otherwise acquired.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Bound transcripts of correspondence between Roosevelt and Henry Cabot Lodge, 1884-1918 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, chronological, 1882-1918; undated; 12 folders (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Edith Kermit (wife) (Box 1)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore Jr. (son), 1919-1937 (Box 1)
  - Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt (sister) (Box 1)
  - Unidentified (Box 1)
  - Incoming (of others), 2 folders (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Album, "Rough Riders," "Campaigning," etc. (Box 2)
  - Portraits (Box 2)
  - Portraits, "Rough Rider" (Box 2)
  - News photos of T.R. Jr., Governor of Puerto Rico (Box 2)
  - News photo, return from Europe (Box 2)
  - Kermit Roosevelt and wife (Box 2)
  - Kermit Roosevelt before committee (Box 2)
  - Roosevelt and family (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Roosevelt, Christmas (Box 2)
  - Edith Roosevelt (Box 2)
  - Edith Roosevelt, 78th birthday (Box 2)
  - Quentin Roosevelt (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Clarke, John. "Random recollections of campaigning with Colonel Roosevelt," 16pp and sc. (Box 2)
    - Finch, Justice Edward. Elegy on New York State Supreme Court Justice John Proctor Clarke, 13 Jan 1932 (Box 2)
    - Roosevelt, Theodore (II). Miscellaneous printed material (Box 2)
    - Union League. Proceedings of the Feb. 14, 1878 meeting, "Theodore Roosevelt Sr.: A tribute." New York. Published by request., 1902 (Box 2)
    - Wolf, C.B. "They 'cust'." 2pp, ts., undated (Box 2)
    - "Off to make 93 speeches" clipping (Box 2)
  - Speeches
    - General (by Roosevelt)
      - T.R. "Duty First." Issued by the Republican National Committee., 1916 (Box 2)
      - Roosevelt, T. "What T.R. says." From the Congressional Record, 1904 (Box 2)
      - T.R. "A Decoration Speech." 3pp ts., undated (Box 2)
    - In memoriam (about Roosevelt)
      - "Assembly Chamber Memorial Services in honor of the Hon. Theodore Roosevelt", 1919; invitation (Box 2)
      - Order of Service, Memorial, 9 Feb 1919 (Box 2)
      - Butler, Nicholas, 6 Feb 1919 (Box 2)
      - First Reform Church, Albany N.Y., 12 Jan 1919 (Box 2)
      - Harding, Warren G., 29 Jan 1919 (Box 2)
      - Hughes, Charles Evans, memorial speech (Box 2)
      - NYC Police Department at the opening of the Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Room, 300 Mulberry St., New York City, 16 Mar 1925; dedicatory address (Box 2)
      - Proctor, Edna, memorial poem (Box 2)
      - Republican Club Resolution, 20 Jan 1919 (Box 2)
      - Roosevelt House Bulletin, vol. 1 no. 5, published by Women's Roosevelt Memorial Association (Box 2)
      - Stoddard, Henry L., 6-11 Jan 1919; reprinted from New York Evening Mail (Box 2)
      - Wilcox, Ausley, 1919; memorial, reviewed by TR before original publication (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Itineraries
    - for Gov. Roosevelt, undated (Box 2)
    - Campaign of 1900 (Box 2)
    - South Dakota, undated (Box 2)
    - North Dakota schedule, undated (Box 2)
    - for Sunday, Sept 16, 1900 (Box 2)
    - Wyoming schedule, undated (Box 2)
    - Colorado schedule, undated (Box 2)
    - South Dakota schedule, undated (Box 2)
    - Tour of President to Pacific coast, 1 Apr - 5 Jun 1903 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Bullock, Seth, undated; sheriff of Deadwood, South Dakota and friend of T.R.; pictured with cowboys (Box 2)